The Balchoth made frequent raids on settlements on the east side of the Anduin until most of the inhabitants fled. Then Cirion, the Steward of Gondor, learned from his spies that the Balchoth were amassing a great army to invade the province of Calenardhon on the west side of the river. The defenses there were too weak to withstand an attack. 
Cirion prepared to lead an army to Calenardhon, and also sent six errand-riders north to ask for help from the Eotheod, who were old allies of Gondor. The errand-riders had to pass through hostile territory patrolled by the Balchoth. Five of them were lost, and the sixth - a man named Borondir - was pursued by the Balchoth during his 15-day journey. He finally made it to the land of the Eotheod at the source of the Anduin on March 25, 2510, and delivered his message. 
Eorl the Young was the leader of the Eotheod. He realized that if Gondor fell, his people would soon be in danger as well. Eorl amassed an eohere - or army - of 7,000 armed Riders and several hundred mounted archers. On April 6, the Eotheod began their southward journey of over 500 miles. 
April 15, 2510, the Balchoth crossed the river en masse into Calenardhon. Gondor's only hope was to see their allies arrive hastily, for another foe was preparing to attack on their rear.