Battle involving Dwarves, Elves, and Men against Orcs and Wargs at the Lonely Mountain. The Battle of the Five Armies was fought late in the year of 2941 in the valley between two great spurs on the southern side of the mountain. The Men of Lake-town led by Bard and the Elves of Mirkwood led by Thranduil had come to the Lonely Mountain seeking a share of the treasure recovered from Smaug the Dragon by Thorin Oakenshield and his company. Thorin barricaded his company inside the mountain and sent for help from his kinsman Dain of the Iron Hills. When Dain arrived at the Lonely Mountain with 500 Dwarves, a battle was imminent with the Dwarves on one side and the Elves and Men on the other.
But then Gandalf alerted them to the approach of an army of Orcs and Wargs. The Orcs came from the Misty Mountains led by Bolg. They were angry with Thorin and Company because the Dwarves had earlier escaped the Orcs in a struggle that resulted in the death of the Great Goblin. Bolg also had a grudge against Dwarves because his father Azog had been killed by Dain at the Battle of Azanulbizar.
The Orcs assembled at Mount Gundabad and then marched eastward. Some of the Orcs were mounted on wolves. The Orc army was accompanied by packs of Wargs, and a cloud of bats flew overhead. 
The Dwarves, Elves, and Men agreed to unite against their common enemy. They arranged their forces on the spurs of the mountain hoping to trap the Orcs in the valley between them. The Elves arrayed themselves on the southern spur, while the Men and Dwarves took up positions on the eastern spur.
A vanguard of wolf-riders entered the ruined town of Dale in the valley and swiftly overcame the small force of Men positioned there. The Orcs and Wargs then poured into the valley. The Elves attacked first with a volley of arrows, and 1,000 of their spearmen charged into the valley below. The Orcs fell back, but were immediately attacked from the other side by Dwarves and Men.
The Orcs panicked and began to retreat. Some of the Wargs turned on their allies and began tearing apart dead and wounded Orcs. But then a group of Orcs who had climbed the mountain attacked the defenders on the spurs from above. The Orcs in the valley regrouped and rejoined the battle.
As the day wore on, the sky became dark with stormclouds. The sky was also darkened by the bats that harried the defenders and attacked the wounded.
Bolg came onto the battlefield surrounded by a bodyguard of Orcs with scimitars and a pack of Wargs. The Men and Elves were driven back to defend the spurs. Thorin Oakenshield then came out of the mountain and rallied the Dwarves of the Iron Hills to him. Many Elves and Men joined the Dwarves, and they drove forward into the valley. But their numbers were too few and their flanks were unguarded and they were soon surrounded. Thorin himself was mortally wounded.
At that moment, Bilbo Baggins - who was on Ravenhill with the Elves - noticed the approach of the Great Eagles from the Misty Mountains. The Eagles swooped down and attacked the Orcs on the mountainside, throwing many to their deaths. The Elves, Dwarves, and Men rallied one last time in the valley below. Then Beorn the shapeshifter arrived in the form of a bear, and he slew many Orcs including Bolg.
The Orcs and Wargs were defeated. Those that fled were driven into the River Running and the marshes around the Forest River, or were pursued to the borders of Mirkwood where the Elves dealt with them. It is said that three quarters of the Orcs of the northern Misty Mountains died that day.
Many Elves, Men, and Dwarves were also killed in the Battle of the Five Armies. Thorin Oakenshield died of his wounds, and his nephews Fili and Kili had died defending him.
After the battle, a Dwarf realm was re-established in the Lonely Mountain and Dain became King under the Mountain. Dale was also rebuilt under the leadership of Bard, the new King of Dale. Both realms prospered and had peace for many years until the Battle of Dale during the War of the Ring
