On the 10th March 3019, Sauron prepares to unleash his orc hords on Middle-earth. However, Gondor stands in his path. He has to crush the Gondorians with a decisive victory by taking Minas Tirith, the Capital of Gondor, but this cannot be done without protecting his flanks.
The proud citadel of Cair Andros stands on an island and gives a total control of the surrounding lands at the north of the Pelennor Fields. This is why Sauron needs to seize Cair Andros from Gondor, and calls Saruman to honour his alligeance
. Now, a combined army from Isengard and Mordor draws near to this Gondorian stronghold, while lord Faeldir prepares to defend agains the assault of Saurons force.